<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Section xmlns="urn:com.io7m.structural:8:0"
         title="Overview">

  <Subsection title="Introduction">
    <Paragraph>
      The <Term type="package">laurel</Term> application attempts to provide tools to assist with
      <Term type="term">image captioning</Term>
      within the context of
      <LinkExternal target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Machine_learning">machine learning</LinkExternal>.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      In particular, the application is geared towards the management of smaller datasets (in the range of thousands of
      images) for use in techniques such as
      <LinkExternal target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fine-tuning_(deep_learning)#Low-rank_adaptation">
        LORA
      </LinkExternal>
      training.
    </Paragraph>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Features">
    <Paragraph>
      The <Term type="package">laurel</Term> application provides the following features:
    </Paragraph>
    <FormalItem title="Features">
      <ListUnordered>
        <Item>
          A user interface for managing images and captions for those images.
        </Item>
        <Item>
          A caption categorization system for assisting with keeping captions consistent across large datasets.
        </Item>
        <Item>
          The ability to import captions and images into a dataset from a directory hierarchy.
        </Item>
        <Item>
          The ability to export captions and images into a directory for use in training scripts.
        </Item>
        <Item>
          A persistent undo/redo system that can store every change ever made to a dataset, including the ability
          to effectively revert to an earlier version at any time.
        </Item>
        <Item>
          A carefully-engineered Java API for manipulating datasets; the command-line tools and user interface are thin
          shells over this API.
        </Item>
        <Item>
          Datasets are backed by <LinkExternal target="https://www.sqlite.org">SQLite</LinkExternal> for reliable,
          transactional updates, and a file format that is designed to endure for decades to come.
        </Item>
        <Item>
          Command line tools for automating operations such as importing, exporting, and interrogating metadata.
        </Item>
        <Item>
          The application is comprehensively documented; you are currently reading this documentation!
        </Item>
      </ListUnordered>
    </FormalItem>
  </Subsection>

</Section>
